[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at
se-radio.net sc radio is brought to you
by the ieee computer society by ieee
software magazine
online at computer.org software
[Music]
hello this is justin baier for software
engineering radio
and today i'm speaking with haroon
williamson and sven schleyer
haroon is a principal security architect
at sebia with a passion for mobile
security and risk management
he has supported companies as a security
coach an architect
a security engineer and as a full stack
developer
sven is an application security expert
with hands-on experience in web and
mobile penetration testing
and is a principal application security
consultant living in singapore
he is also the creator of the owasp
mobile hacking playground
both sven and haroon are project leads
for the owasp mobile security testing
guide and mobile application security
verification standard
so just to start off the episode i want
to talk a little bit about mobile
application development and then work
into the security discussion
so back in episode 300 we discussed
mobile app development with jonathan
stark
and i'd refer listeners there for a more
in-depth discussion
but just to start off what kind of
mobile applications can be developed
i know that there's native apps and web
apps and hybrid apps and progressive web
apps
sometimes called pwas you know what are
those
and how do they differ from a security
perspective from one another
so if i can have a little jump on that
one if you look at mobile apps and i
don't think i'll have to go
very deep detail but it's nice to have a
small trip down memory lane i guess
in the very old days uh we didn't do
mobile native apps at all of course we
just had a
website that was loaded into a browser
on the device and we tried to tailor
that towards a mobile perspective
so you basically have all the audits of
a browser stack all these you should
normally have and you're actually
visiting a mobile website so that's just
where we started off then basically
the whole jump into native apps came but
they became too
complicated to the native app you
basically don't have their browser stack
anymore but you're trying to run
directly into the runtime of the
operating system and then
the hybrid app game where we said okay
let's try to use for instance the
webview
and render as much as we can over there
so we still have the same mobile website
feeling but at the other end let's try
to use those native things as well
for instance try to uh work with the
fingerprint
uh scan scanning a later point in time
but at first of course like stuff like
gps to start to know where you are and
all those type of features let's combine
them
we had a very long time a promise of the
performance that it would be better than
a mobile website and it would be easier
than a native app but what we ended up
with for a lot of years was basically a
very slow application
that had all the vulnerabilities of a
webview and all the vulnerabilities of
raw implementations of those plugins so
security wise we still weren't there
but at the other end otherwise you had
to run to the complicated native app
then of course you have progressive web
apps where you have web service workers
downloading the content on priori and
making sure it would still work
and then you go back to how well is your
browser's tech defined how well did you
secure it over there and you
start over that party again so overall
if we have to rate that
i think still depending on how well you
wield your tools
i think a native app can be the most
secure but that does mean you have to
stick by the book
and you'd end up with two different
co-bases or
a framework that is tailored towards
having
native compilations so you start with
something like xamarin yes you start
with xamarin for instance and all they
do is compile towards
the native app sdks you don't do
anything else and in the end you do they
need to do some tailoring from time to
time depending on the version and how
well it was
developed over time but at least you get
all the security features you need
but then again when it comes to adding
anti-reverse engineering and other
tooling you
again have to jump into the native code
base so overall native is indeed
easier to secure i would say but it
comes with a price
you as a developer have to work pretty
much harder to get all that extra out of
it and it's really a question if you
need that i mean overall if you have a
marketing app you want to get it out
yesterday
but if you want to secure your banking
that's a bit of a different
game altogether yeah and that's
definitely something we'll dive into a
little bit more when we discuss you know
threat modeling and picking
where you actually need to be on the you
know security spectrum of things but
that's definitely an interesting way to
put it so essentially when you look at
something like xamarin
you know you might get some of those
higher level security benefits with some
of the ease of use
of having you know one single code base
that i can compile across the whole
you know landscape of devices that
microsoft wants to support for it
whereas a native app you know i might
have five different development teams
because
i need to develop an app for ios and app
for android and then you know
the 500 other kinds of android that you
know are running on t-mobile versus you
know verizon versus whomever's
uh custom version of their kernel
so essentially what you're saying is
you know when i'm running a high
security app or something where i need
to implement things like
any reverse engineering or more secure
network protocols and
have that lower level hook in i need to
look at a native app versus
these other kinds of apps yes definitely
definitely
so if it comes to the higher level stuff
like securing your network we got a
browser stack that's
uh nowadays pretty much okay if you got
support for
scientific transparency and other stuff
to do a lot of basic vetting
but the moment you are afraid that
specific attacks might happen where a
lot of additional headers are stripped
off for instance yet then you have to up
your game but it's really again your
threat model
if you think your users are only at home
and they
have a separate vpn where the
communications happen across or
something
you then have the network stack it's not
really that important at all
but if you look at the current state of
things like with covet 19 many people
have to stay home anyway so that's a
whole different network security game
altogether
but if you now look for instance at
before covet 19 where people in
different countries used to hang out in
pubs and
you know oh i forgot that your friend is
telling that he did this and this and
now you still oh you had to pay that so
you now
have to go online and quickly because
your mobile banking told you it was this
easy
so you want to go there then all of a
sudden you're on the insecure shared
wi-fi
because you forgot that you should have
turned on fiji instead of your you know
wi-fi
and then we can end up with an old
different security
frame in terms of the network stack that
you're running on and then all of a
sudden pinning and all the other jazz
becomes important
okay so again it's a mix of both you
know
from my app what am i doing in my app
and how secure do i need to make it for
my users by default without forcing my
user to think about it and go
oh i was on the shared wi-fi hold on let
me get on the lte because that might be
a little bit more secure or at least in
my head it might be a little more secure
exactly so moving a little bit off of
just the discussion of mobile apps and
what kinds there are
you know just to make an easy comparison
most developers i would argue are doing
something with web apps of some kind
today and most developer education
is focused towards you know building the
next sas app and
all those things so how would you say
that a web application
differs from you know mobile
applications on a security perspective
you know
what are the different areas of concern
that i'm going to have for a mobile
app versus a web app so just just a few
things i mean
during a web application test that you
would do from a from an attacker's point
of view
so the the major things that are really
different is the amount of data that is
actually stored in a mobile
app so when you look at web apps of
course there's also a lot of data stored
but it's just getting more and more in
terms of
mobile apps that is being stored i mean
we have heaps of gigabytes nowadays
available
and the mobile apps make also extensive
use of that meaning a lot of data
is actually there and it's of course
also very easy in order to store this
information securely with ios and
android if you make a native app
but still there's a lot more information
that is actually stored in mobile apps
the other thing that tyrone was already
mentioning is then the reverse
engineering factor also
so especially a lot of apps if you think
now about otp
apps also about banking apps
especially gaming apps they have a huge
attack vector of reverse engineering
because a lot of the logic is also
within the game
also with an otp apps and if you find
then
the actual algorithm that you that you
can break that you need to break
and that allows you then to reverse
engineer the actual process and for
example generate your own otps if you
stick with the otp example
or you might be able to cheat in games
then you will have a
big attack vector and that might
actually really have an impact of the
companies especially in games so reverse
engineering is definitely one of the
big impacts that you have for mobile
apps compared to
um compared to web apps yeah and i'm
assuming that you know unlike games on
your computer you can't have an
anti-cheat engine that's running from
you know boot if we look at you know
some of the newer anti-cheat engines
whereas
you know on a mobile device we're
actually talking about we're going to
have to implement something to
obfuscate the code in such a way that
you know i'm going to prevent against
reverse engineering
but just changing directions a little
bit local storage is definitely
something that's
unique to mobile versus web so how do
you protect that
you know in your app against someone
losing or getting their device stolen
you know
are you 100 reliant on the actual
underlying
operating system implementing some kind
of protection via pin or passcode
or is there something you can do within
your app to actually protect the data
that you're storing in there
like let's say you're storing
certificates for some reason or another
in your local storage for your app how
would i protect those kinds of secrets
within it
there is an mcg we have the a nice uh
comparison in terms of security which
you can get basically
and what we always start off with is if
you're not afraid of
data being stolen in that sense you can
start off at least as close to the
secure world as possible
so start with using stuff in the
keychain
or have key in the in the android key
store with strongbox encryption so
start as strong as possible but the
moment you
you might be afraid of something going
wrong then it's better to
actually move that control after that
away from
the mobile device but move it towards
the server so with the app you
authenticate towards the server you get
your decryption key and your currency
can start decrypting the local content
and the moment your device is told you
just block your app instance for
instance
and then you're pretty sure nobody can
access the data anymore and then the
more you go
towards having keys or data stored
something like share preferences or
secured part of the android storage or
the
lesser more secured file system of ios
the more you start opening yourself up
to a lot of different attack vectors
especially if there's no interaction
with the server necessary anymore
because that means the moment the device
got stolen
and the passcode might be easy to guess
or the device got obtained while being
unlocked for instance and kept unlocked
they got a whole different thing but as
you can already hear while i'm telling
this
we all of a sudden start introducing
different threat scenarios
so the moment you think like okay i'm
only worried about it locked device
being stolen it's fine with just moving
keys into the secure world and you know
having your passcode to protect that
but it also immediately minimize sets a
limit or a bar
for your minimum ios and android version
because prior to those we didn't have
hardware keys so yeah you can't service
those anymore
at the other end if you're afraid of a
device being stolen or
robbed because there's really a higher
risk towards your app
you then you need something else but
then you're always too late anyway
but let's say you want to have more of a
hybrid model because you
want to allow users to have their
devices unlocked for hours
which is not really what we would
recommend in the first place in terms of
privacy of course but you know people
people are people and they want ease of
access so they want the simplest
guessable passcode anyway
because i'm always forgetting my
passcode and it's so hard and
the light in my face is so heavy when i
have to do face authentication so let's
do this differently you know those type
of things
then we have to start interacting with
the server at least so that at least at
some point in time when their easy to
unlock device gets stolen
of which a lot of your users will have
because you're not creating a
complicated app for a complicated advice
user you're creating an app for the
masses
so you want to make sure you can also
service that
that boy or girl or women or or man that
doesn't want to go all the way in
securing stuff he just wants it to work
because he never figured security and
why should he because his life has been
secure enough till now until his device
got stolen
and then if that's your third model then
you should start thinking about let's
make sure you got the server in there in
that handshake that that you got the key
from the server and yes then the user
has to authenticate yes that's a hassle
but apparently you have something so
much of high risk data on the device
right now
it's worth it but if you combine these
things the wrong way around it gets
hairy so it really starts with actually
having a proper thread model
and then the line starts you know
similar like reverse engineering you can
start pick what you want there yeah we
had done an episode with adam shostak
discussing
uh threat modeling i don't think it's
published yet as of the recording of
this episode but
in discussing that it almost makes me
think of you know
in some cases an app for a general user
you may not necessarily be worried about
the data that's stored on there let's
say an email application
but once i go to a corporate environment
now i'm starting to worry about what
kind of data sitting in it
and maybe this is less of a you know
from a vendor perspective saying
yes our app is 100 secure all the time
no matter the user no matter the use
case we'll protect your data whether
it's
you know cat pictures or your you know
million billion dollar you know
intellectual property
and instead saying look we'll do our
best but if you want to implement these
things you need to look at something
like a mobile device management solution
where
you can enforce these kinds of controls
like face id
or you know having you know 15 digit
pin codes that can't be 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8
10 you know and circling back again you
know
that the enforcement necessarily doesn't
live within the app but is instead on
the actual
operating system side almost like the
discussion
and i guess this would be an interesting
comparison to here you know would you
say that it's
almost closer to how we used to worry
about
application development and security in
that traditional you know client server
architecture when we used to stick a
hard client on someone's desktop and say
you know run this application it'll
connect to our server in the back end
and then it'll pop up on your machine
versus the current model of yeah just
open your web browser and go to the web
page it's available everywhere here you
go
i think there's quite some similarities
to it indeed because
in the end you end up with hopefully
that client being secure enough to do
something whereas the web makes it more
easier but at the other end
if you go back to the old client that
client had much more capabilities
which we don't have with the web in its
current shape of course the web is
changing all the time so we might end up
with no need for mobile
native apps eventually but we don't see
that yet
so in that sense there is indeed some of
those things going on in there but the
difference is when we look between think
client and doing web first so
go from client server technology to a
more of a different
uh software as a service model you can
see that
we already tried launching away from
native apps to sas a bunch of times and
every time we start walking back
so that's a bit of a different journey
whereas with the you know the science
journey we go
well let's say up i don't know left or
right but you know more
towards the server again and at the
native we had cordova
we i bet you could over exist for quite
a while
we got quite a lot of different hybrid
technologies as well
but for every one of those you can see
that they're used by some
but eventually we ended up with again
more native apps
and now we have a lot more different
frameworks that are being used which
have
great results i mean if you look at some
of those hybrid app technologies
nowadays they're pretty fast and it's
looking beautiful
but again we see also new native apps
popping up next to them
so it's not like it's a journey that
went off towards sounds like we're used
to
at the other end to be fairly honest if
you look at managed workspaces you see
that the thing client is coming back
again but then purely in the cloud so
i don't think we really went away from
the think client model as well
in the amount that we would like to
believe ourselves
but from a consumer perspective yes we
did and we love it
i mean check it out chrome firefox
safari will bring you anywhere
but overall for many different company
environments we end up using that same
chrome to connect to a remote
desktop web interface and we start over
with a thin client just with a web
interface on top of it but we're
back at the same thing again so yeah
it's a journey
yeah i always like to think of the uh
you know microsoft remote app you know i
stick a remote app proxy in front of my
on-prem app and now it's a sas app sort
of kind of ish maybe
yes so changing directions a little bit
here
and you know kind of a silly question
here you know
we've mentioned it and kind of covered
it but i just want to make it really
clear
when my app is interfacing with the api
i still need to worry about all those
api security issues and
you know all those authentication issues
and the session management or
you know cross-site scripting issues or
you know local file
you know inclusions that's all still a
problem even if my mobile app is 100
secure right
i mean all of the different things that
you were just mentioning um
like crossout scripting for example this
is only an issue if you have a web view
so for all the different things that um
was already mentioning
like for example submarine or cordova
whatever is webview based
then things like crossout scripting is
definitely something you need to
consider and
you would need to take care also in your
mobile app development it's not actually
about the authentication
and also authorization all of these
things this is something that we do not
really
cover under mobile security testing yet
i mean we touch it definitely
and we explain it also but it's
something that is
more on the server side and on the
client side
it's very similar then to to web apps i
would say i mean on top of that
you have the benefit of using things
like local authentication we were
already talking about
like where you have this additional step
like biometric authentication
but um in that sense it's shifting a
little bit especially with things like
cross-site scripting also
there's always an added nastiness
towards it because the moment that you
start
uploading photos to an api from your
native app
who's guaranteeing that a native app is
talking to your api
at the moment you start believing as a
developer that oh it's only the mobile
app and nobody knows about this so
apparently you did
enter reverse engineering to kind of you
know get that away
and all of a sudden the jpg starts to
have very funny binary code in there
we're getting a bit into trouble now
aren't we so in that sense remote file
inclusion still
lives i mean you can't trust what a
mobile app is uploading because you
don't know what the mobile app is
indeed like as film is already
mentioning that's not where the mscg is
designed for
of course we have a few controls in the
misvs and also quickly describe the mcg
to remind you of the fact that you have
to implement your security controls at
the server
which automatically means that these
kind of filtering need to apply over
there as well
but we already have many funny cases at
different customers where people
were so beautifully focused at the
mobile app that they forgot that other
agents can access their api as well
unfortunately
so having my slash mobile endpoint is in
a
safe security mechanism to prevent you
know these security issues
and as you're mentioning you know this
isn't something necessarily in scope for
the mobile application security testing
guide and
you know that kind of stuff and maybe
this would be a more appropriate
you know looking at and the owasp realm
the web security testing guide to
actually review those apis and
you know verify our authentication all
those kinds of security things
and then be able to say okay our api
secure now let's make it work with our
mobile app
yep exactly awesome so now
just diving in a little bit here what
would you say
would be common areas that developers
when they're building their
you know mobile apps should be focusing
on from a security perspective
so what it should really focus on
is starting always out with the threat
model because the moment you start
enumerating controls
it's endless of course at the
mobilification security verification
standard we have a level one on level
two and always start at level one with
the hygiene
controls you require a great example is
for instance if you look at
network and storage where we start with
the basics so don't
at the storage level before we start
talking about encrypting your storage
and stuff let's start with okay only
store stuff
that you really need to store and leave
other stuff at the server
if you look at network don't start
pinning immediately let's just first try
to have a decent certificate chain in
place let's just first try to make sure
using decent protocols
and then we move ahead so start with the
basic hygiene
and the mas vs can clearly guide you by
the means of level
what you should do first and of course
if you have a proper trad model you can
always say no to certain level 1
controls because you believe that the
risk it's covering is so little
that you're okay with that the funny but
sad and consultancy answer it is it
depends
unfortunately and really it starts with
threat model first
then take the hygiene controls that
you're really sure of and then the once
you debate it in your model
and then if you still have a lot of
risks left that you really need to cover
start
jumping into the higher end controls so
it really starts with
basic input sanitization don't store
stuff you don't need to store
get your network security controls in
place make sure that you did your
authentication properly wherever
necessary
and if you thought about the
authorization model together
let's make sure you have something like
architecture documentation and that
sounds a bit weird and i know as i did a
lot of development work
we don't really like writing
documentation that much to be honest i
mean many of us don't
but if you don't have a common
understanding of what you're doing
it doesn't matter what you do because in
a year time when the next development
team
will have the problem not me anymore and
they start
you know breaking controls because they
had a different understanding of things
they get worse
so let's make sure you first get common
understanding so it's not only about the
mobile controls you implement but it's
also about the process around
development
let's make sure we first do our proper
software engineers and
take our work serious take collaborating
series take documents here so we know
what we're doing nobody asks you to
write a bible
not at all just make sure that we
understand why this code is there
and not that the code speaks for itself
magically you can always hear my votes
when you read the code no that's not how
that works
let's make sure we first understand why
that code had to be written in the first
place
and once you got at that level stop
your it will it will vary massively in
terms of what you have to do next
it really depends on what you're
building and why
hiring a software engineer then we
recommend working with g2i
g2i is the most effective way to
discover talented and pre-vetted
engineers for every project
g2i vets their talent pool through
technical interviews and various code
challenges which are graded by actual
engineers
saving you time and guaranteeing you top
quality through their transparent
grading
they specialize in react react native
and node.js
interested in learning more then go to
g2i.co
yeah and just to dive in i know you had
mentioned um
you know certificate pinning i know sven
mentioned earlier web views
i just want to dive into a couple of
these things just to make it clear to
our listeners you know what these things
are so
would you be able to give me a quick
summary of what a web view really
is and how you would actually go about
securing that web view
let me maybe please answer that one so
um a webview is just a very simplified
browser in that sense in a mobile app
so for example you will not have your
url bar and other things like that so
it's very simplistic
and so you can see this a lot in those
hybrid apps also that we were talking
about earlier
and in order to actually secure them
properly there are a few different flags
that you can make part of a webview when
you're defining or
when you're defining your webview and
your code one of the first things is of
course disabling javascript
which many times of course will not be
possible because many times you
do want to use javascript but a few
other different things that you can do
in order to
harden maybe your webview so for example
different kind of url handlers that you
want to
block like access to the file system for
example that is part of the sandbox
so there's still different kind of
attacks where you have um file inclusion
also within the mobile app
so this was demonstrated also while back
so you need to
harden your webview as much as possible
which is as i was saying
javascript the url schema that you
should be blocking that you do not want
and um also for example on android
there's something called add javascript
interface and this is where it can
become a bit dangerous
because this is where you're bridging
more or less your code your java or
kotlin code and android
with the javascript interface to your
webview and if no somebody is actually
man in the middle or has maybe some
stored xss
already placed on the server side then
this javascript piece will actually be
able to execute the code that is
available via the ad javascript
interface
and if this is something sensitive then
it can become quite dangerous so this is
where
you would need to understand what you're
actually exposing via javascript
interface in your web view
fantastic thank you for explaining the
web views a little bit so essentially
it's just a trimmed down browser sandbox
that has a lot of its own issues on top
of the
built-in browser but are those the same
kinds of issues so like for example
you know if i had a vulnerability in
safari
on ios the web views would still be
impacted by that same kind of
vulnerability
so for web fuse it's um it's a bit of a
complicated thing
because the webview you're working with
might not be the webview you think
you're working with in general
the engine you're using in your browser
might be is different brander platform
is different quite a bit for ios
platform for the main browser like
chrome and uh the embedded internet
application pictures your android
application with your android platform
or the version of safari and then the
webview you were offered in earlier
versions of android was again
quite a different thing so they came up
with a beautiful idea and i think that's
actually quite brilliant
to have a installable webview like the
chrome webview that you can upgrade
through
uh the enderplay through the google play
store which helps a lot with having a
more secure webview
but then again you should wonder and
maybe okay
if you have to wonder this let me first
make that note that you might go into
the wrong direction at this point in
time
but the moment that you're starting
running on that webview you don't know
which version is there so you don't know
what's vulnerabilities you're working
with in general
of course you can check for the version
but it would be kind of sad that if you
open up your app
you're asking your customer to first
upgrade your chrome webview via google
play store before you can continue i
mean i don't think that's really
the way to do this but overall you just
are not sure what you're going to have
there
and of course many of those browser
engines have a lot of
commodities in terms of how stuff is
implemented which will indeed affect
both the webview as well as the browser
so you're ending up with both things at
the same time
the only difference is of course if you
open up the browser stack
and you're vulnerable at the browser
level for a certain odd execution path
all you get for free is what you
normally would also have in your normal
browser
so that's how you would handle a mobile
website and there's not a lot of
edit complications in there but the
moment that you're having that mobile
app and you figured okay we found ways
to secure our data so let's
open up that webview and all of a sudden
that sandbox with that secure data is
opened up towards the same web view so
now we increase the risk
so there's two those three things
basically come to that
okay so essentially you know web views
are going to increase your risk but it's
not exactly the same as the browser
that's running on the device and it can
be all kinds of different depending on
which
operating system you're running on on
the mobile device overall just trim it
down
like sven told and that would really
help exactly only use what you need and
enable what you need rather than
enabling everything and then turning
things off selectively later
and then you had mentioned certificate
pinning and not necessarily worrying
about that out
right at the start when would you want
to start to worry about that what
exactly is that going to mitigate
so i can give a very lengthy answer in
that it would tire your
your listeners a lot i gave a
presentation about it that to pin or not
to pin
which was focused on ios and one also
focused on both platforms i think it's
great to include the links
but there are three things that should
always come back the first thing if it
comes to pinning is
if you look at the attention areas you
should wonder about is okay
is my user in a network environment
where this makes sense so when
we can be eavesdropped so is it on
public wi-fi
do i really not trust uh any of the cell
networks in the country that my
user is at for instance you can easily
imagine that
some of the more government-controlled
countries might have a different network
layout than those who are a bit
different basically like and then still
you might wonder what the government can
or cannot do but the moment you start
worrying about those
you're interesting you're developing a
quite interesting app i would say
the thing you should more be worried
about is what is my user doing
if i have some sort of financial app and
i want to secure the communications and
i know my users are greedy and we'll
start install those
beautiful free apps that you can sign up
in ios as long as you click ok on the
next device profile per certificate that
you really need to install this app
yeah so for the developers not knowing
what's happening right now
basically what many people do is uh try
to do is
skim people into installing apps for
free like clones of those or not even
clones and even functional clones but if
you get the idea it's for free
and you have to install a certificate
with that and that certificate can then
often be used to
bypass any network communications
because it's uh similar to the
certificate offered by the by by the
server that's he's dropping basically or
that's the man in the middle
at the other end in the netherlands we
had this beautiful story of the
notar and just google it that's because
otherwise you can rent on on tds
insecurities in general for ages and i
don't think that's
the proper thing to do right now but the
nice thing is that
we that basically proved that the moment
the ca gets compromised
attackers can hand out certificates for
any domain so the moment you're really
worried about your network
in in terms of what you communicate with
your server if you're really worried
about the protocols you've been using to
authenticate and people might reuse that
material for
lesser good let's say that's the moment
you start thinking about pinning
but then there's two other issues to
think about if you want to protect
the keys that you're using via pinning
and use those keys for a longer period
of time
are you actually able to secure the
private key of that key pair well enough
at your server and as a team that you
want to put all the extra effort into
reusing that key for a very long time
at the other end saying which you shift
keys more often and we have a different
strategy so we forget about bidding in
general because it's hard to do key
management or secrecy management as well
you might have different face to fry so
it starts with do i don't trust the
network or is the risk too high
then yes i can start pinning on my
public key but then still ask yourself
am i really able to protect the private
key well enough that it makes sense to
pin towards the public key
okay so essentially it's that you know
risk versus
reward benefit you know how much do i
really trust the network and as
with everything in security it
eventually ties back to your threat
model where are your trust boundaries
and you know when you talk about zero
trust we always say you know we don't
trust the network until we establish
trust in the network and
those other you know newer security
approaches but
maybe from that sense of you know do i
really need to worry about certificate
pinning in adults additional workload to
the development team
you know it really becomes that risk
worse's reward or can i just you know
rotate certificates every you know year
or every six months
instead of you know worrying about this
very long-term public key
hash pin to verify that they're using
the correct certificate when connecting
to my application exactly
of course we can ease the pain by making
sure you got the public key set up and a
bunch of backup keys as well just make
sure you don't store the private key at
the same location as the other private
key that might have been compromised and
yes we've seen customers do that
so that's where you can start off with
so like your you as a mobile app
developer don't have to worry
but just make sure you did communicate
to your server guy
that he shouldn't be deploying something
else in the things you agreed on
because then you basically kill the app
communication again and more importantly
instead of
thinking about is my network secure is
thinking of is my
protocol secure and that's of course
basically so how long would a session
last so if i start authenticating
to authenticate with something like
secure remote password protocol where we
don't
send the password at all but we send
something else over the wire that
the server and the client have to
calculate blah blah blah or do we
do some sort of harder to replay
mechanism where we sign off messages
and so you can't you can see stuff but
you can't
change them that could already help a
lot but of course if you have your
standardized app with a standard
way of authenticating and you can easily
replay those things and you're worried
about that
then you should think about pinning if
you notice your app is used a lot in
environments where it's easy to to
eavesdrop basically
which does combine with what's the
version
of the operating system you're running
on for instance ios got
ats already in there quite a long time
so a lot of hygiene is being
done by the operating system already and
with newer versions of android it became
much harder to use custom supplied
certificates
where instead of the operating system
ones so
if you only have these guys and girls
and whatever with
very modern devices and you based your
development on that then again there's
less worry you need to have about that
but the moment you want to support
everybody
including those people with very old
devices where these controls aren't
there
then pinning might not be such a bad
idea in general as long as you take care
of the things we just talked about
maybe just one thing to add from here
roon is also the operational aspect i
mean you have all the technical
components that you need to implement
but you still need to be sure that the
operation team that is maybe
changing the certificate on your servers
actually talking to the development team
because i could see in the past a lot of
clients that were quite happy to finally
implement ssl pinning and one year later
they actually had a denial of service
against their user base because the
certificate was updated
without updating the certificate in the
app so this is also something that you
really need to take care of and is quite
crucial
when you're implementing ssl pinning
okay so it
it's not just the you know can i develop
it and put it in the app but can i
actually
operate this architecture and system to
support this you know do i have the
appropriate automation in place to
you know ensure that if a certificate
gets changed on our infrastructure i can
change it on all these mobile
applications and
not cause a huge denial of service so
by implementing these you know secure
network communications does that
actually
help with some of the you know
conversations around spoofing cell
towers on lte
with you know i know law enforcement
uses the stingray device but it's been
shown that you can actually do that just
from
you know your computer with some you
know network cards is there
any actual security benefit from that
perspective by doing these types of like
certificate pinning or is there
something else you would have to do to
protect against that so it starts with
certificate pinning or actually public
key pinning because like you already
beautifully mentioned indeed the hashes
so
you rather been against the hash of that
key than the full certificate so we have
less work we need
and it can really help because the
moment somebody starts
uh jumping into the network and now
there's a bit of um i'm not sure is
has there been a previous episode where
tcip was covered a bit before we start
talking about spamming trees and all
that jazz
i think we've done a little bit of
network coverage um but i don't think
we've delved too deep into the concepts
of spanning trees and you know remote
spanning tree and the different
protocols in that sense
okay so let's keep it simple the moment
you're in a wi-fi you're sharing that
with others that might be consuming
depth that you're developing
or that you know as an attacker you're
in the same space as the guy with the
banking app just keep it simple
then that guy if the computer in the
same wifi network can start saying to
all the computers
hey the shortest path to the internet is
at this
address come along let's celebrate and
all the computers go like and all the
mobile devices go like hey
okay that's indeed a shorter amount of
apps and that's very fast let's go there
so now from the solos place we
start doing stuff like that now we can
start seeing the lower level of
communications
which is awesome or awful depending on
which side of the tree you are of course
i mean
seriously but in the end where it then
bounced to is what did you do at a
higher level
so at the tls level the moment you have
public key pinning in place and now this
computer starts offering certificates
for
different for the domain of your banking
app
but it doesn't fit with what you got in
your app then you're secure the only
thing is of course is that this banking
app no longer works
and i've been trying everything and it
doesn't work and that's just weird
so the worst case scenario is that you
as a developer or as a
bank a provider get a nasty review on
google play like hey
um come on man my app is not even
working in here so yeah but
that's maybe not as bad as having to
explain the bank why the money got lost
so in that sense it's about it's an
ongoing team during this conversation
your ted model and next to that it's
about
okay so how far do you want to go so in
that sense it does secure against these
type of attacks for
quite a lot of course the moment you
have
access to the device spinning doesn't
make sense it doesn't do anything so the
moment i can
during this network conversation install
some sort of malware or offer something
else in your device that
basically goes a level deeper than the
current app communication
pinning doesn't help at all but that's
quite hard
so in that sense then having pinning can
help a lot
exactly so it's like that conversation
we have on the endpoint side once you
have administrative access or root
access it really doesn't matter what the
app does to secure it it's game over
once they have the operating system
exactly so just changing directions a
little bit
how do you see the security internals
differing between
you know the two major operating systems
on mobile devices ios
versus android you know is there
huge differences in areas like how
data's stored
or how you would implement local
authentication or how you would
implement anti-reverse engineering or
you know the secure network
communications i know you had mentioned
a little bit about you know once you
start getting into these
more security focused things now you're
bumping your version levels up and now
you're not supporting everyone
but just kind of focusing on i guess
we'll say the latest versions of these
things
you know what do you see is you know the
big security internals in these devices
and how are they beneficial
to you as a developer i would say that
they are in many areas actually quite
different
quite quite the same meaning for example
on ios you have your local
authentication with different kind of
biometrics
you also have the same thing on android
with local authentication through your
iris scan through your finger whatever
as hiroon was already saying when it
comes to data storage on android you
have the key store
um on ios you have the keychain so there
are many things that nowadays are very
very similar you could say
in terms of security it has changed over
time but i would say the major
difference and this is where it really
becomes inconsistent on the android side
is on ios as a developer
i can just assume that there is a secure
enclave i can use the keychain
and all the different hardware things
actually available and this
is very very different to android
because on android when you run when you
when you develop an
android app you obviously want to have a
huge
customer base meaning you would actually
need to go down quite a bit
into the older android versions that
maybe have that maybe cannot support all
the different features
or maybe do not even have all the
hardware features there are a lot of
cheap android phones for example
for example they do not even have a te
or secure enclave something like this
so it's not really a hardware packed key
store and in these areas i would say
it's actually the big difference in
terms of security because some of the
devices
um have actually a lot of limitations
already in the hardware simply because
you have such a zoo of different
vendors and and hardware vendors yeah so
essentially that single source of
hardware from ios does give it that ease
of development you know you kind of know
what to expect if you're on xyz ios
version because you know exactly what
device they stopped supporting that
version on
exactly yes and in ios it's just very
very easier to to maintain because you
know that these hardware features are
there and they're there for all hardware
devices of all devices
so between ios and android would you say
that you know
one of them has better process isolation
so for if example i'm running you know
i downloaded a malicious app and it's
running in the background and
now i download your app and i start
using it for you know making my
million dollar banking transfer to my
other account
you know does one of them provide better
security in that sense
so to answer that question we have to go
a bit trip down to memory lane because
it has different quite a lot
although i first have to make a big
disclaimer i'm more of an application
security specialist
if you look at the asp project behind
android if you look at the amount of
code that has been published till now
anyone that hasn't been in terms of
how ios has been built up there's so
many things to say about that and
there's
awesome presentations from specialists
that are specialized in that field
like look at 2desco and other people and
everything you should really dive into
them
into that area but if you look at the
application consuming part so what we
can do as developers because i think
that's something we can answer
then there's been quite a journey for
both android and ios
so for instance android intents we used
to start over with having everything
open if you just call this intent you
end up somewhere and then we ended up
for instance with extra security control
saying okay you can only
use this uh process enterprise
communication
if you're signed by the same key at the
moment
you got released into the app store so
you can make sure that only certain app
components can talk to each other if
they're from the same vendor for
instance
at the other end you got ios where they
started using things like entitlements
to further secure
the claims required to do certain
inter-process communication which helped
a lot in securing that communication
but overall of course these are controls
that are implemented on the application
level
and how well the boundary beyond that
has been
secured so you really have to use this
pulse that has been
quite different and that's harder to
assess of course in terms of what's
better what's not better
what we've seen so far if you look at
attacks like the overlay attack for
instance
in android where malicious app will then
just make you think you're communicating
with it but in the meantime it's just
clicking through to the other
application
and then doing the actions it wants to
that's been giving a lot of
attention in android for instance which
is indeed has been quite a problem for a
while
at the other end if you look at the
keyboard users for instance
uh we saw that on android you had custom
keyboards quite soon so everyone like oh
yeah custom keepers bad idea
but then at some point in time apple
opened it up as well because hey custom
keywords are awesome because you might
want to have a different way to
communicate
and then people realized we're now in
the same pile of trouble as we are in
android in that sense
and then when it comes to shared
clipboards it's get a bit a bit harder
because how do you want to for instance
that
your password uh application communicate
with that application you want to
authenticate that
because you need a way to let that
communicate and if all you have left is
the clipboard
yeah then both platforms have the same
problems
so in that sense if it comes to those
share platforms that's you know
designed to be open we get in trouble
basically on both platforms but if it
comes to more detailed things after that
luckily there's beautiful talks by
different people that are specialized in
that and
it's a great thing to watch although as
a developer you'll learn lovely things
about low level programming
and i would really advise you to do it
in general so you can
enjoy the ease of the work we have to to
develop our apps basically
so do you see a benefit you know
and you mentioned the signed apps
concept you know is there a benefit to
the ios
you know almost walled garden approach
to the app store whereas on android
we're seeing you know more of a
wild west where signed apps is kind of a
optional additional feature if you'd
like to use it sort of kinda whereas
you know on the apple side you know
you will go through our app store and
you will be signed unless you know
excluding the concept of a jailbreak
device yeah so that's um
that's an interesting thing it starts
with actually let's go
zoom a little bit into the walled garden
because remember we started talking
about
bypassing the tls hygiene by installing
that site loaded app
so there's still a bunch of website that
offer installing site loaded up on ios
in general as long as you allow that
developer certificate to be installed or
some other
certificate that signed that up and then
you can still use those apps
of course that doesn't mean that that
app all of a sudden gets control over
the complete device or whatever because
you still need to access it right
or yes it might hold some other bypass
that we don't know about which will
get you into trouble but if you look at
what androids is currently working with
yes there is a much bigger amount of
wall wear statistically in android than
ios for instance so in that sense
android has a lot more security issues
so having a walt garden type of approach
where you have a strict review and you
can't just download anything
helps indeed quite a lot at the other
end we also see
because of that a faith of developers
into apple will fix this
so why should i encrypt using keychain
can't i just use the shared preferences
i mean seriously who's jailbreaking his
iphone anyway
and then all of a sudden we forgot about
things like pokemon go
people being too lazy to walk around
with gps or going to japan for the final
pokemon and still wanting to obtain
those and therefore jailbreak it
and just whoop there it is we got the
full open space and that simple site
loaded up will give you all the problems
you had before
so if you're sure that your users are
not one of those
and that means you need to know your
users
good luck with a multi-million user app
yeah sure then
indeed you get certain guarantees
because apple looked at everything that
got installed on that device
but if you don't which is exactly the
case with a multi-million user app
then the pitfall you have with this
security approach is that you think
apple took care of everything for
everybody and nothing will ever happen
so why should i do this additional
control why should i encrypt something
why should i use the keychain
specifically because we're okay
that becomes a serious pitfall the
moment you start jumping into that
of course if you still take security as
serious as you would
on an android device then the walt
garden approach gives you a lot of
benefit
in terms of the actual security of the
runtime that you're running on
given that users indeed update do their
thing
play nice don't wanna sit in their
beautiful bottoms when they play pokemon
go but you know
actually do stuff the way they're
supposed to okay so there's benefits the
wall garden
you know especially from a security you
know application developer perspective
you're doing checks for you know a
jailbroken device you're doing checks
for
you know side loaded applications and
you know detecting that these things are
occurring around your app
to be able to say hold on wait i don't
want to run on a jailbroken device
because of our threat model
that you know we don't like our
financial app running on jailbroken
devices
and then of course there's a problem
with that unfortunately so the world
garden helps in the fact that if
everybody plays nice we're okay but the
moment people don't play nice they can
also try to hide the jailbreak
detection of course so they hide the
jailbreak they make it harder to detect
to do other things because they still
wanna play pokemon go
without moving around they still wanna
be able to use their devices to use to
while having that jailbreak so as long
as you can assume
that it's okay or i mean if you assume
that people
are playing by the rules then having
walt garden helps
but the moment you know but the moment
you have a two bigger user
base that can use this consumption app
for virtually anything
then you know that this doesn't help you
for your specific app
it just only helps those that really
play by the rules so for instance if you
have like a corporate device
that's locked down and your corporate
users only use it for business sign off
contract
blah blah blah really play by the rules
and i haven't seen anybody who did but
let's assume that we are
then this helps but until then you have
to do the same thing as you would do in
a non-walled garden
environment take security serious just
make sure you implement those controls
and don't think because apple will
review your app for not making some of
the mistakes but don't think that the
user might not have
tricked itself in to do certain things
to this device
that makes some of the things you
thought you didn't need to implement
very key to implement to prevent that
data leakage
okay awesome so just again if you're
developing on the ios i just
don't assume that apple is fixing
everything for you you know actually
do the threat model for your application
and decide what needs to be done
so now a little more into that and
talking a little bit more about what you
guys both do as your
you know side project what products have
you guys created out
of the oaus mobile appsec project so for
this one
um we need to go back maybe a little bit
three four years um for this
i was still working as a penetration
tester and one of my colleagues who was
bernard miller
or ben we were doing a lot of mobile
application penetration tests and we
could see that there's actually a lot of
inconsistency in mobile testing not only
from the pentester side
but also on the developer side so a lot
of the things that we were already
discussing today
there was not a really clear direction
is ssl pinning now vulnerability
is do you really should disable all the
things in your web view
so there were a lot of things scattered
around the internet and different great
blog articles in github and i don't know
in
great books but there was not really an
industry standard and that's
in that sense so we had the web
application testing guide
from overs that covers everything on the
api but there was nothing in terms of
the of the actual endpoint in terms of
the mobile client
so there was a lot of inconsistency and
we wanted to
drive that change in that sense back
then to become an
industry standard which i can say we we
also achieved in recent years
and while we are doing this project back
then
we had a mobile security testing guide
which is just a very
verbose technical explanation
how you can test certain aspects or
certain parts of security in your mobile
app
but while we were doing this we could
see that we are merging test cases we
are splitting
them again and we had a lot of
inconsistency while we were writing this
and then we were actually creating the
masvs which is the mobile application
security verification standard
very clunky very long work so it's the
masves and
this we were focusing first back then it
was like three and a half years back
in order to get all the different
requirements i mean we were
emphasizing and describing already quite
a lot about them about
data storage about the network
communication ssl pinning webview and so
on
and we were grouping all of these
requirements together
as part of the misvs so these are
requirements that are os agnostic
and this became now our baseline you
could say and these are roughly 80
requirements at the moment
and once we had these requirements we
could actually start with the mobile
security testing guide so these are the
main
two projects that um hiroon and myself
and also others are working on
so we have the masvs that is summarizing
all the different requirements
security requirements specifically for
mobile apps we have the mobile security
testing guide that is outlining these
different requirements into technical
test cases
and then we have the excel sheet that is
trying to bridge these things
so that we have a link from the masves
to the mstg and on top of that
created a few other things we created
the overs crackmes these are different
mobile apps for
ios and for android
where people can really get their hands
dirty and try to hack those apps
then we have the hacking playground that
we created which so they direct me
somewhere for reverse engineering
bypassing different client-side security
controls then we have the hacking
playground which is again something
where you can try to get your hands
dirty again with the different test
cases
and i think last year hiroon was also
starting a site project
in order to map the submarine google
flutter and all of these different
things from the masves into these hybrid
frameworks because they are a bit
different
i guess we can also put this into the
show list so that people can also get an
idea of that this is still work in
progress
but this is where we also want to map
this not only to native apps
but also to these um hybrid frameworks
so essentially you have you know the
verification standard is kind of the
overall you know that's where i think
you know as her mention the leveling
you know the different levels of that
you would pick based on your threat
model
and then you take the mobile security
testing guide to actually test and
verify that you're meeting those
standards
and then i think there's also a
checklist that you can use
to ensure that you're meeting the masbs
requirements
exactly maybe to quickly elaborate
because i was not mentioning that for
the misvs you were just mentioning the
different levels
so in the masves we have this we have
the level ones and these are baseline
security requirements this means every
app
should have the security requirements
built in
and on top of that and this is now again
where we come to the threat model
if you have specific threats then
there's the level two this might be ssl
pinning and then we have another
category with
which is resiliency against reverse
engineering so these are your
route detection jailbreak detection all
of these things i'll have links to
all of those things in the show notes um
herm can you actually talk a little bit
more
about the um project that you're working
on mapping the standard
over to those hybrid apps so over
the last one and half years we got many
requests from people like hey
how do i do this in the xamarin app how
does it works in apache cordova and then
funny enough we actually see a growing
flutter base as well where the same
questions are being asked
so given that we're not hybrid
specialists because that means you have
to dive into that stack
very deeply and understand it what
happens how does it get cross-compiled
whether and where
i i basically gave a shout out to the
community like hey
what we're gonna do is the following if
you think this is important
spend some time with us here the google
drive sheets and update those
some of them are still quite empty which
shows that there haven't
been enough interest from the security
community at least to
give traction so i hope well let me just
use five seconds of your time
dear listener if you are a security
expert please go to the show notes and
check those google sheets and if you
really want to help your hybrid
developing colleagues
start filling them in we would love you
to help us out
thank you very much i will definitely
include a link to those of the show
notes
i also wanted to dive a little bit into
the hacking playground
is there you know any way that a
developer could leverage that
to you know help them understand you
know the verification standard
or what a pen tester is going to be
looking for based on the testing guide
and you know understanding you know
this kind of code is bad this kind of
code is good and
this kind of code could go either way
and this is how i would test for that
yeah this is exactly the intention i
mean when we were starting with this
whole project four years back
and the hacking playground was just more
or less the output of our research
research in order to demonstrate how bad
code actually looks like
so that pentas does of course know how
it's uh
how it should shouldn't look like and um
in the mstg we are bridging that
actually
usually in the in the static analyzer
section so in the
mstg we always have the same structure
we have an overview
where we just explain what this test
case is actually all about
then we have the static analyzers we're
actually making a deep dive into
the different keywords that you should
be looking for as a pen tester but we
also give a
best practice usually for the developers
what you should do in order to mitigate
the findings
and then there's the um dynamic
analyzers part meaning what you as a
pentastar can do to analyze an app
while the app is running so the hacking
playground was just more or less the
things that you can use as a developer
or maybe also for security trainings
to really illustrate how you can easily
hack something
and just to demonstrate all the bad
practices that you shouldn't do so that
a developer can just get the ipa
or the apk can install it play around
with it the source code is available on
github obviously so they can just
change it in whatever way they want
maybe even fix the issues
and see if the fix actually works or if
there's still some way to bypass it
so it was just to get a kickstart for
for people to to get them started and
play around with it
awesome so it's similar to almost in the
website
you know web goat or you know the
oas juice shop you know hacking examples
you know that way you can see you know
this is what bad code looks like this is
what good good looks like this is how
you'd fix it and then from a security
training side you can even take that
and sit with the developer and say hey
like let's go through this code and see
what's wrong with it why it's wrong what
would be broken
and then in that developer's head they
can then kind of draw that line and go
you know i used that function last week
when i was writing some code maybe i
shouldn't have done that that way
exactly exactly and on top of that we
also have the correctness that that just
purely focus on reverse engineering
so for the correct me which are part of
the mstg project
we also have a very good write-ups
because a lot of great people
were solving them and were writing those
write-ups into their blog posts
so even though that reverse engineering
is usually not a skill set of developers
but if you want to dive deeper into
this you can also just go to our crack
me page
and go through the different blog posts
because they explain it really in a lot
of detail how they were using different
kind of
tools like either or gydra or whatever
in order to break those tools and of
course frida which is
one of the favorite tools for reverse
engineers nowadays awesome so
essentially you know that may not
necessarily be something that a
developer is going to do out of the box
but
at least being able to go through these
walkthroughs and say
oh wow it really is that easy to reverse
engineer these applications maybe i
shouldn't
stick the secret in my uh you know
shared config space or in
a plain text config file sitting in the
application folder
yeah exactly there should be a lot of
aha moments
so just changing directions a little bit
we have the testing guide we have
you know the verification standard you
know theoretically a developer is going
to sit there
or you know a development manager or a
project manager
is going to sit with the security team
and they're going to say all right so
based on the threat model that we've
created as a group
you know we've agreed that this project
is gonna have this verification
level you know it's gonna be a level two
and we need to implement any reverse
engineering
and you know we're gonna take these
things and we're going to take all these
standards
and say let's verify against this
how would i take those and now actually
integrate that into my project is that
something that you know i'm going to
stick in my ci cd pipeline is that
something where
you know it's going to be manual
verification with the checklist and just
going through and saying
yes we've done this yes we've done this
yes we've done this so that really
depends on the controls that you're
implementing
so let's let's go a little bit back
let's again take the tls
uh configuration as a starting point so
it's relatively easy to
take your application in its runtime if
you want to or just decline with which
you're connecting to and try to
create an integration test where you
basically offer something else and it
should have been connecting to and see
if it breaks
so for a lot of things it's easier to
develop your own tests and it goes
actually back to
why should i do that the moment you got
your own tests that you can run on every
change to see if you didn't break the
security controls it's the best thing
you can do
because the faster the feedback you get
the better it is because the less time
you're spending on other things
and that comes together with the fact
that the moment you are writing tests
for it as a developer you start to
really
understand what's happening because it
might well be possibly while listening
to this podcast that you've been
assuming that tls works in a certain way
and that
you're did a great job in the
configuration or that you did something
completely wrong
but while you're writing the test you
might find out something completely
different because now you have to ask
yourself
what should have happened what should
have been the end game if i set this up
this way
and by writing your own tests that is if
you have the time and budget for it of
course
it becomes a much easier to understand
what you're doing and b it becomes much
stronger to make sure that you don't
well
get into a messy situation later point
in time if you go one level
further away you get stuff like the bdd
mobile security like david schoco
created which is an open source testing
framework for based on the mscg
which is beautiful because then you let
an external testing suite
check whether you implemented certain
controls correctly which means
you get a little bit of less
understanding or at least you need to
spend less time on that
you can really focus yourself on getting
that business value out instead of the
security value part
and then one level further away is just
using more of a commercial suite that
you don't need to tailor but does
some of the control testing and then you
have to make sure that it's okay
because you're not really sure but some
for some it's
quite well for some controls it's very
effective but so for some controls it'll
be
quite hard so if you want to be sure for
instance that you didn't store
something with a wrong write on your
application it's very easy to have a
scanner checking if you did something to
the sd card or the public document
directory
in terms of secure storage validation
for instance
but if you want to validate whether you
did your obfuscation correctly
that's going to be quite tricky because
every time you obfuscate or they
obfuscate i hope you have a different
path
because if not you're not deficient
correctly um
which means that now all of a sudden you
have to start creating a very odd
testing suite or just have more of a
mental verification to see what's
happening
because testing these type of things
will be way harder of course so
first of all depends on how much you
want to learn how much you want to make
sure you can get feedback asap but you
broke the control with some of your
changes
and uh letter of course is the type of
control you're verifying so whether it's
an l2 more difficult requirement or an
entire reverse engineering requirement
kind of going back to the start of your
discussion by building tests i have to
actually understand the underlying
protocols of what's happening not just
benefit from the abstraction and walk
away and say
well it was apple's problem to implement
tls correctly not mine i don't care
about what the config is
not my problem all right and just one
last thing before we
you know start to wrap the show is there
any benefit to taking
you know and i kind of mentioned this
earlier you know you know you have your
project management team and all that
kind of stuff where they're
you know going to look at something like
msvs and
you know decide what level we really sit
at you know with the security team and
deciding you know what's our threat
model that kind of stuff
is it something that you would want to
leverage in your early architecture
phase like how could i leverage these
things in an early architecture phase
you know
when we look at like more formal things
like you know sabser togaf or
you know a less formal model like you
know i draw my uml diagrams and that's
our app
architecture have a nice day how can i
leverage these tools to help
improve the security from an
architecture perspective
moving into a development i mean usually
it really makes the most sense if you
already use whatever the developers are
using so when you're
just creating your different use cases
then from a security point of view you
of course just want to
think malicious and make them abuse
cases so meaning you really start very
very early and just try what can
actually go wrong what can go wrong with
the confidentiality with the integrity
with the availability
of all the of all the data of the
network communication what goes wrong if
this goes down
and you really want to break this
use cases into abuse cases and this is
where the masves can actually help you
and this is where we can
where we are coming back to the threat
modeling and what you actually do
is you make different kind of threat
modeling dependent on your on your
different use cases to see what is
actually
um working or not working awesome so you
know you're leveraging the standards to
almost help guide you from a security
perspective
to say here are the abuse cases or even
as a developer if you want to try to get
ahead of the curve to say
you know okay well these are the things
that security is going to look for so
let's think about
you know how we're going to want to
implement these how we're going to want
to implement it into our project
management cycle be it agile waterfall
what have you
you know and creating those use cases or
abuse cases and
you know integrating it into the actual
project
design in the architecture design
exactly i mean the thing is that as a
developer you
most likely will not be aware of all
these different um attacks and
requirements but this is exactly where
the masvs comes into the picture i mean
i'm not saying you should now
read everything end to end but if you
have these kind of use cases and you're
trying to think and put your hacker hat
on maybe let's phrase it like this
and then the me svs can definitely help
you guide through
and this is where the levels also come
in place first focus on level one
then on level two if you really have
everything done and
you're paranoid enough then go for the
resiliency and the reverse engineering
controls
fantastic just to wrap up the show and
i'll ask both of you this question
started with roone is there anything
that i didn't cover that i missed that
you think a developer or a software
engineer should know thinking about it a
bit of it because
it's been a wonderful show so far thank
you very much now i think you
cover the most important topics so like
webview
storage uh network security
how to use the tooling i think those are
all very important
one thing that we always you know talked
around a little bit of course
is authentication authorization of
course not related
strictly to mobile but i think that's
one final pitfall to always
remember an app developer about the
moment that you start talking to an api
there's no difference between web and
mobile that you have to make sure that
nobody can read the messages of somebody
else unless he really has to
so that doesn't change when you do
mobile i think that's the only thing we
missed
other than that great yeah i think we
covered everything that's
of importance yeah and i've referred
developers back i know a lot
of things are moving towards you know
the oauth standard of authentication on
the api side and stuff like that we did
an episode which
had a lot more detailed discussion on it
episode 376
and we've also done an episode
previously
i believe it is 383 with neil madden
on securing your api uh where we
discussed a lot more
of those web security discussions around
apis and what kinds of vulnerabilities
existed and how you'd mitigate it
and sven same question for you you know
is there anything that i missed or
that heron didn't mention that you would
want a software engineer to come away
with
you know after listening to this episode
i think
we actually really touched almost all
different areas so i think that was a
quite packed show
i guess the only thing that i would like
to add is that in terms of
tooling in terms of security tooling
that can actually help you
i would say it's quite limited and
there's not really
so what i mean by that is it's just very
very diverse as we could already hear
the beginning of the show we have
progressive web apps we have native apps
we have hybrid apps
there's just so many different kind of
apps and then on top of that we have so
many different frameworks we have react
we have cordova with submarine
and having now different kind of
security testing tools of course is
quite hard especially if you're a big
enterprise
and you have a lot of different diverse
frameworks
then the tooling in that sense might be
quite limited when it comes for example
to source code review
so i think the most effective way in
order to really build security in the
start early start with threat modeling
and really identify what you want to
focus on
and this is where you can really
leverage on a lot fantastic thank you
i just want to thank both of you for
coming on the show and you know
discussing mobile application security
and all different kinds of issues and
how we can leverage you know different
testing tooling and you know
integrate it into the development life
cycle thank you very much it was really
a pleasure to be here and an honor
have a lovely show and thank you for
listening thanks for inviting us was
really great to be on the show justin
thanks for that yeah of course this is
justin baier for software engineering
radio
thank you for listening thanks for
listening to sc radio an educational
program brought to you by ieee software
magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at
se radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at
scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening
[Music]